acas.org.uk 2019-12-06

# Acas website: privacy policy | Acas

Your rights relating to use of your personal data changed in May 2018, when the Data Protection Act 2018 came into force.

This Privacy Statement explains how and why the Advisory, Conciliation and Arbitration Service (Acas) processes your personal data under these new laws.

If you have a query about this Privacy Statement please contact the Data Protection Officer at the contact details below.

## How we use your personal data

Acas collects personal data about you to fulfil the legal functions it is required to deliver under the Trade Union and Labour Relations (Consolidated) Act 1992.

What we collect about you and how we do this depends of what Acas services you might use, and how much personal data about you we need to provide these services. These are explained below.

### 1\. Acas Helpline

The telephone number you use to call our helpline is recorded in our helpline database. This is kept for a maximum of eighteen months. At the end of this period, your phone number will be deleted from our database.

We keep your phone number for this period to identify your call to monitor the volume and nature of helpline calls we get.

We may make an audio-recording of your call and use it for training purposes. You will be informed of this with a recorded message before you speak to a helpline adviser. We keep recordings for training purposes for 30 days then they are destroyed.

We may also record your call to check that our wider services meet everyone's needs. If we decide to use your call for quality improvement, we will delete your telephone number. This makes it impossible for Acas staff to know who made a recorded Helpline call when using it for this purpose.

We may refer your call to another part of Acas (for example, to our Conciliators). If we do this, the Helpline may pass on relevant personal details about you (including name, contact details, and details about your workplace). We only pass these details to other Acas staff who will deal with your case. 

### 2\. Early Conciliation or Conciliation services

We collect and use personal data to provide Acas' Early Conciliation or Conciliation services. This is the same whether you are a 'claimant' making a claim, or as a 'respondent' - an employer responding to a claim. 

This personal data will include your name, address, and workplace details. Acas may also collect and use further personal data required for your case, including sensitive personal data (for example medical information, trade union membership, or racial/ethnic origin) if this is needed.

Acas staff use this personal data to contact claimants and respondents, and to conciliate in cases as part of our statutory duty to help resolve employment disputes.

We may also use your personal data to check that our conciliation services meet your needs. We sometimes use external research organisations for these checks.

We will not share details of your conversations with the conciliator with the other side in your dispute, unless you give us your clear permission to do so. This is the same for telephone call notes, emails and letters.

We do not make audio-recordings of telephone calls with conciliators. This is so Conciliation cases remain as confidential as possible.

Our conciliators make case notes of the conversations they have with you and the Respondent which they store in a case management system. This is also where they store emails and letters. This is kept for 6 months after a case is closed. 

Personal identifying data, such as claimant and respondent names, addresses, telephone numbers, and email addresses are retained for a further 6 months after case notes and correspondence are deleted.  

After the two purges, case references, jurisdictions and (on ET1 claims only) the gender of the claimant, are retained for research purposes only.

### 3\. Collective Dispute Resolution

Collective conciliators keep names and contact details of the trade union representatives and employers which they speak to. This is so they can help if there is a dispute. Collective conciliators may keep these details until they are no longer needed. If you wish a collective conciliator to remove your contact details because you have moved job, or trade union role, please contact Acas at [dataprotection@acas.org.uk](mailto:dataprotection@acas.org.uk) with the details of your request.

Collective conciliators sometimes process personal data as a third party. This occurs when collective conciliators are invited in to organise ballots or conciliate in trade union recognition disputes. 

On these occasions, personal information is not collected directly from the individuals (or 'data subjects'). Lists of employees/workers are given to Acas by an employer and lists of trade union members are provided by trade unions.

Data collected may consist of: Name, Employer, Trade Union Membership number, Name of Trade Union and dates of births of both workers/employees and trade union members. Employers and trade unions make an agreement in each case which information is given to Acas.

Acas keeps these lists for one month after the announcement of the results of a ballot or a membership check has been made and then destroys the lists. Collective conciliators keep names and contact details of the trade union representatives and employers which they speak to. This is so they can help if there is a dispute. Collective conciliators may keep these details until they are no longer needed. If you wish a collective conciliator to remove your contact details because you have moved job, or trade union role, please contact Acas at [dataprotection@acas.org.uk](mailto:dataprotection@acas.org.uk) with the details of your request.

Collective conciliators sometimes process personal data as a third party. This occurs when collective conciliators are invited in to organise ballots or conciliate in trade union recognition disputes. 

On these occasions, personal information is not collected directly from the individuals (or 'data subjects'). Lists of employees/workers are given to Acas by an employer and lists of trade union members are provided by trade unions.

Data collected may consist of: Name, Employer, Trade Union Membership number, Name of Trade Union and dates of births of both workers/employees and trade union members. Employers and trade unions make an agreement in each case which information is given to Acas.

Acas keeps these lists for one month after the announcement of the results of a ballot or a membership check has been made and then destroys the lists.

### 4\. Training services

We collect and use personal data to provide training services, workshops or projects for people who make bookings with our customer services team and our website. 

When you make a booking we collect your name, address, telephone number, e-mail address and workplace details in order to process your request. You may also volunteer any special needs you may have (such as dietary requirements if food is required for a training course). As Acas charges for its training services, we may retain personal data collected for this purpose for seven years. This is so we comply with finance law.

We will store your personal details through your on-line Acas training account. This will be stored for as long as you keep your account. This is so you can look at your account history.

Acas may use the personal data collected to provide you with Acas mailings for marketing purposes, to check that our services meet our customer's needs, or to inform you of changes to our services.

### 5\. Use of personal data for internal research

We collect and process data to create a body of knowledge to help us give advice, conciliate and provide training services. Our researchers collect and analyse personal data for the following reasons:

  * Customer insight, in which we collect and analyse data on our users' experiences, behaviours, needs and characteristics
  * Product research and development
  * Marketing research
  * Research of Acas' wider external environment, in which we collect and analyse data on policy, economy, technology etc.
  * Insight from external stakeholders
  * Insight from Acas' own staff
  * Analysis of Management Information detailing the activities of our customers/users/delegates

We may use personal data collected as part of the services we offer, to also conduct research into employment trends and on the performance of Acas in meeting user's needs. You will be informed of this when signing up to use our services.

If you use our Helpline or use our Website, we may additionally ask if you are willing to take part in Acas research, for example as part of a user survey. If you agree we will collect personal data from you e.g. contact details, for this purpose.

Where we do use personal data for research purposes, as far as possible we will try to make this unidentifiable before we use it. This is to help ensure that your privacy is respected when personal data is used by Acas staff for research purposes, or by those providing research services to us.

We may share personal data to be used for research purposes, such as email addresses, with external research companies that have been employed by Acas to carry out research and analysis on our behalf. Where this happens, we will ensure that use of your personal data complies with the law and is kept secure at all times.

In addition to the information in this notice, which covers a range of research and analysis conducted by Acas, there may be some project-specific information, which we will provide separately. This will usually be at the moment you are invited to provide data (eg complete a survey or take part in a focus group), in an email, on an information page on a website, or orally. This information will most likely cover the name of any third-party agency processing data on our behalf, and their representative's contact details. If you do not have this information, you can email [research@acas.org.uk](mailto:research@acas.org.uk) to request it. Please give as many details of the research project in question to help us identify the information relevant to you.

Some research projects differ from our usual methods to such a degree that they require their own privacy notices. If this is the case, you will be provided with such a privacy notice, and this general research and analysis privacy notice will not apply. If you are unsure which privacy notice is relevant to you, you can email [research@acas.org.uk](mailto:research@acas.org.uk) to ask. 

### 6\. Making a Freedom of Information (FOI) or Subject Access Request

If you wish to make an FOI or Subject Access Request, your contact details and case history will be collected to process your request and will be kept for two years.

If you wish to make a complaint to the Information Commissioner's Office (ICO) regarding a decision on a FOI or Subject Access Request, Acas is legally obliged to share your case records, which includes personal data, with the ICO in order to progress your complaint. You may withdraw your complaint at any time.

## Sensitive Personal Information

Some of the information you provide to us may be sensitive personal data, such as medical history, criminal convictions, trade union membership or racial/ethnic origin.

We will only ever use sensitive personal data where this is essential to provide advice or to provide one of our statutory services such as conciliation. We may also use medical information you provide to make reasonable adjustments to help you access our services, or to ensure dietary requirements can be met where needed.

## Confidentiality, storage and security of personal data

The confidentiality and security of your personal information is very important. Any personal information you provide will be held securely, and your personal information will not be sold or traded to another organisation or company.

In order to carry out our functions and respond to enquiries effectively, we may sometimes need to share information with government departments, the emergency services, law enforcement agencies, and public authorities (such as the Employment Tribunals Service). However, we will only do this where it is permitted by law.

We ensure that personal data shared with an external company or service that we employ as part of our work will be held securely. Your personal information is only used by them only to provide the services or information that you have requested.

Acas safeguards the information you provide to us using physical, electronic and management procedures. For example, industry-standard Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) encryption is used on web pages where we collect personal information electronically over an internet connection.

We manage risks around the use of personal data using the '10 Steps to Cyber Security' framework, managed by The National Cyber Security Centre (a part of the government). Security of our Information Technology (IT) systems are evaluated using Her Majesty's Government (HMG) Security Policy Framework.

Customer, claimant and respondent data is held in a government secure data centre in the UK. Back-up services are also provided in a separate government secure data centre in the UK.

## Lawful basis for processing

Under data protection laws, Acas must have a 'lawful basis' to justify our collection, storage and use of your personal data. Where sensitive personal data (or 'special category' data) is used, we also need to have a second lawful basis to justify our use of your sensitive data.

The purpose of most activities where Acas processes personal data, relates to our legal duties under the Trade Union and Labour Relations (Consolidated) Act 1992.

Our lawful basis for processing personal data is:

  * For 'ordinary' personal data - 'Task in the Public Interest' (Article 6(1)(e) GDPR) and " the exercise of a function of the Crown, a Minister of the Crown or a government department" Data Protection Act 2018 (c. 12) PART 2 CHAPTER 2 Lawfulness of processing Section 8 (d)
  * For 'special category' personal data - 'reasons of substantial public interest' (Article 9(2)(g) GDPR) and " the exercise of a function of the Crown, a Minister of the Crown or a government department" Data Protection Act 2018 (c.12) Schedule 1 PART 2 Substantial Public Interest Conditions Section 6 Paragraph 2 (b)

You can find out the difference between 'ordinary' and 'special category' information on the [ICO website](https://ico.org.uk/).

## Your rights under data protection law

You have a right to request a copy of the information that Acas holds about you. You have the right to have any inaccuracies corrected.

You may also have the right to have your personal information erased; to restrict our use of your personal data; to object to our processing of your personal data; and to obtain and reuse your personal data for your own purposes across different services ('data portability'). 

You may also have rights in relation to automated decision making and profiling.

You have the right to complain to the national authority on the use of information, which in the UK is the Information Commissioner's Office

Please address requests (with a return e-mail address where possible) to:

The Data Protection Officer

Acas

Strategy Directorate

22nd & 23rd Floor, Euston Tower

London

NW1 3JJ

Email: [dataprotection@acas.org.uk](mailto:dataprotection@acas.org.uk)

## Use of our website and Social Networking

When you visit our website, we collect your Internet Protocol (IP) address as a unique identifier. We also collect the following:

  * data about how you use the Acas Website
  * information about your computer (including your IP address and browser type)
  * demographic data
  * if you visited the Website by clicking on a link from a different website, we collect the URL of that website
  * information about your online activity, such as the pages you have viewed and the purchases you have made.

Our website offers you the opportunity to 'like' or 'share' information about Acas on your social media networks. We also maintain pages on some of the largest social media networks.

Sharing your personal data with a social media network may result in that information being collected by the social network provider or result in that information being made publicly available.

Acas cannot control or endorse any policies or practices of external social media networks whose functionality you may access through our website. You should always read the privacy policy, and check your privacy settings, on any social media network through which you might share information over.

Cookies are small pieces of data sent to your computer when you visit the Website and which enable us to collect information about you. They are stored in the cookie directory of your hard-drive, and do not necessarily expire at the end of your session. Session cookies are automatically deleted when you close your browser.

Our use of cookies also allows registered users of the Website to be presented with a personalised version of the Website, to carry out transactions and to have access to information about their account. Further information on our use of cookies is available on request.

The Acas website contains links to other websites, mainly other government departments, but also to those of other third parties. These websites are not covered by this Privacy Statement and Acas is not responsible for the privacy practices within any of these other websites. You should be aware of this when you leave the website and we encourage you to read the privacy statements of other websites.

## Data transfers

Territories outside the United Kingdom may not have laws which provide the same level of protection for personal information as those inside the UK. However, if we process your personal information on servers or use third party service providers based in such territories, we will work hard to ensure that your personal information is given the same level of protection as in the UK.

## Changes to this Privacy statement

If this privacy statement changes in any way, we will place an updated version on this webpage. If you do not agree with the changes we make please do not continue to use the website. Regularly reviewing this webpage ensure you are always aware of what information we collect, how we use it and under what circumstances, if any, we will share it with other parties.

### Last updated: 09/08/2019
